<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<syllabus>
  <chapters>
    <chapter id="ch1">
      <meta>
        <badge>Chapter 1</badge>
        <badge>60 minutes</badge>
        <badge>K2 Focus: Understand</badge>
      </meta>
      <title>Test Strategy and Test Approach Challenges</title>

      <key-box>
        <heading>Learning Objectives</heading>
        <list type="check">
          <item>Compare test types to be performed during and after an iteration</item>
          <item>Explain when end-to-end testing should be performed</item>
          <item>Compare the benefits and drawbacks of formal testing and holistic testing</item>
          <item>Differentiate among regression test approaches</item>
        </list>
      </key-box>

      <section id="ch1-intro">
        <h3>Introduction to Agile</h3>
        <paragraph>Agile testing is not a phase — it is a collaborative, integrated method that embeds quality throughout the development process and highlights the whole team’s responsibility for quality.</paragraph>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Agile Manifesto Values (2001)</heading>
          <list type="check">
            <item><strong>Individuals and interactions</strong> over processes and tools</item>
            <item><strong>Working software</strong> over comprehensive documentation</item>
            <item><strong>Customer collaboration</strong> over contract negotiation</item>
            <item><strong>Responding to change</strong> over following a plan</item>
          </list>
        </key-box>

        <h4>Key Agile Principles</h4>
        <list type="ul">
          <item>Deliver valuable software early and often</item>
          <item>Embrace changing requirements, even late in development</item>
          <item>Frequent releases with short cycles</item>
          <item>Daily collaboration between business and developers</item>
          <item>Motivated individuals with proper support and trust</item>
          <item>Face-to-face conversation is most efficient</item>
          <item>Working software is the primary measure of progress</item>
          <item>Sustainable development at a constant pace</item>
          <item>Technical excellence and good design enhance agility</item>
          <item>Simplicity — maximize work not done</item>
          <item>Self-organizing teams produce best work</item>
          <item>Regular reflection and adjustment</item>
        </list>

        <h4>Common Agile Methodologies</h4>
        <table>
          <row><cell>Methodology</cell><cell>Focus</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Scrum</strong></cell><cell>Fixed-length sprints, defined roles, ceremonies, prioritized backlog</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Extreme Programming (XP)</strong></cell><cell>TDD, continuous integration, close collaboration</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Kanban</strong></cell><cell>Visual workflow, WIP limits, continuous delivery, flow optimization</cell></row>
        </table>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Definition of Agile Testing (Gregory &amp; Crispin)</heading>
          <paragraph>“Collaborative testing practices that occur from <strong>inception to delivery</strong>, supporting frequent delivery of quality products that add business value. Testing activities focus on <strong>defect prevention</strong> rather than defect detection, and work to strengthen whole team responsibility for quality.”</paragraph>
        </key-box>

        <h4>The Agile Testing Manifesto (Greaves &amp; Laing)</h4>
        <list type="check">
          <item><strong>Testing throughout</strong> over testing at the end</item>
          <item><strong>Preventing defects</strong> over finding defects</item>
          <item><strong>Testing understanding</strong> over checking functionality</item>
          <item><strong>Building the best system</strong> over breaking the system</item>
          <item><strong>Team responsibility for quality</strong> over tester responsibility</item>
        </list>

        <h4>Impact of Agile Testing</h4>
        <list type="ul">
          <item>Testing is integrated into the workflow, not a final gate</item>
          <item>Strengthens collaboration and communication</item>
          <item>Testing roles clarify requirements and identify defects early</item>
          <item>Quality is a collective team goal — anyone can test at any time</item>
          <item>Mindset shift from techniques-only to customer value + adaptability</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section id="s1-1">
        <h2>1.1 Test Types</h2>
        <paragraph>Test types are selected based on test objectives, iteration context, user story acceptance criteria, quality risks, and feedback needs. Decisions should be reflected in the <strong>Definition of Done</strong> and the test approach.</paragraph>

        <table>
          <row><cell>Test Type</cell><cell>During the Iteration</cell><cell>After the Iteration</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Functional</strong></cell><cell>Verifies implemented features meet requirements and acceptance criteria</cell><cell>Expanded integration of features (including cross-team)</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Non-functional</strong></cell><cell>Basic performance, usability, or security on new features</cell><cell>Full non-functional testing on integrated / staging environments; broader exploratory and usability testing</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>White-box</strong></cell><cell>Used before/during coding (e.g., TDD); early defect detection</cell><cell>Rarely a separate activity; code coverage may be measured during black-box testing</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Black-box</strong></cell><cell>Verifies new/modified features against user story acceptance criteria (ATDD)</cell><cell>Broader system-level testing, regression, end-to-end</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Exploratory</strong></cell><cell span="2">Critical throughout; during iteration it uncovers unknown risks and emergent behavior via structured, time-boxed sessions</cell></row>
        </table>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Key Takeaway</heading>
          <paragraph>All test types can be used at any stage, but <em>how</em> they are used differs during vs. after an iteration. Exploratory testing is especially important to fill gaps between white-box and black-box coverage.</paragraph>
        </key-box>
      </section>

      <section id="s1-2">
        <h2>1.2 End-to-End Testing</h2>
        <paragraph>End-to-end (E2E) testing verifies integration across systems and user workflows. It is valuable but costly to maintain and slow to run, so it should be used with intention.</paragraph>

        <h4>When to Perform E2E Testing</h4>
        <list type="check">
          <item>Closer to a release or during hardening iterations</item>
          <item>When system-wide integration points are newly introduced</item>
          <item>When integration points carry high risk of failure</item>
          <item>In distributed systems with complex user journeys</item>
          <item>When third-party dependencies cannot be reliably tested in isolation</item>
        </list>

        <h4>Factors Influencing E2E Decisions</h4>
        <list type="ul">
          <item><strong>Risk</strong> — impact and likelihood of system-level failure</item>
          <item><strong>Feedback time</strong> — heavy E2E suites slow delivery; favor faster lower-level tests</item>
          <item><strong>CI/CD maturity</strong> — automation, observability, monitoring, feature toggles, and A/B testing can reduce reliance on extensive E2E</item>
        </list>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Test Pyramid Reminder</heading>
          <paragraph>Broad, fast feedback at the base (component tests) → fewer service-level tests → minimal end-to-end tests at the top. Deviating increases cost and risk.</paragraph>
        </key-box>

        <h4>Alternatives / Complements</h4>
        <list type="ul">
          <item><strong>Contract testing</strong> — validates service interfaces independently; consumer-driven contract testing is effective in Agile environments where services evolve independently</item>
          <item><strong>Holistic testing &amp; exploratory testing</strong> — uncover unexpected behaviors, usability defects, and edge cases that scripts miss</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section id="s1-3">
        <h2>1.3 Formal Testing and Holistic Testing</h2>

        <compare>
          <card type="pos">
            <heading>Formal Testing</heading>
            <paragraph><em>Precision and formalization; derives test cases from explicitly defined requirements.</em></paragraph>
            <list type="ul">
              <item>Traceability between requirements and test cases</item>
              <item>Aligned with coverage metrics</item>
              <item>Assists verification (built right)</item>
              <item>Conformance to standards</item>
              <item>Repeatability</item>
              <item>Eases test automation translation</item>
            </list>
          </card>
          <card type="neg">
            <heading>Formal Testing — Challenges</heading>
            <list type="ul">
              <item>Excessive rigidity; restricts exploration</item>
              <item>Over-reliance on documented requirements (often incomplete/incorrect)</item>
              <item>Misses unexpected and emergent risks</item>
              <item>Often executed late → delayed feedback</item>
              <item>Low cognitive engagement; mechanical execution</item>
            </list>
          </card>
        </compare>

        <compare>
          <card type="pos">
            <heading>Holistic Testing</heading>
            <paragraph><em>System-wide view of quality; continuous testing across customer, team, and organizational perspectives.</em></paragraph>
            <list type="ul">
              <item>Combines process, product, and user viewpoints</item>
              <item>First Time Right — quality built in, not tested after</item>
              <item>Continuous verification + validation</item>
              <item>Collaboration, context awareness, systems thinking, exploration</item>
            </list>
          </card>
          <card type="neg">
            <heading>Holistic Testing — Challenges</heading>
            <list type="ul">
              <item>Lack of focus without disciplined structure</item>
              <item>Difficult to measure; context-sensitive</item>
              <item>Requires culture change and leadership support</item>
              <item>“Whole team” ownership can dilute accountability</item>
              <item>May not satisfy regulatory / contractual constraints</item>
              <item>Lack of formality endangers test automation</item>
            </list>
          </card>
        </compare>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Complementary Use</heading>
          <paragraph>Use <strong>formal testing</strong> for critical components, high-risk areas, and regulatory requirements — automate where possible. Use <strong>holistic testing</strong> for general quality control, early feedback, and exploring complex scenarios with highest user impact.</paragraph>
        </key-box>
      </section>

      <section id="s1-4">
        <h2>1.4 Regression Test Approaches</h2>
        <paragraph>In Agile, regression testing must support continuous delivery and rapid change. Different approaches can be used individually or combined, depending on context, capabilities, risk profile, and automation maturity.</paragraph>

        <table>
          <row><cell>Approach</cell><cell>What it is</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Incremental regression testing</strong></cell><cell>Automated suite maintained continuously; subset of regression tests triggered per commit/integration based on risk, location, and dependencies. Enables early defect detection.</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Risk-based regression testing</strong></cell><cell>Frequent risk assessments guide automated and manual regression. Helps decide where automation is unnecessary and human investigation adds more value.</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>DevOps-oriented regression testing</strong></cell><cell>Woven into CI/CD; smoke tests as quality gates, high-priority tests post-deployment in pre-prod or prod. Feature toggles, canary releases, and observability may replace traditional regression in some cases.</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Exploratory regression testing</strong></cell><cell>Applied continuously or at intervals; supplements automation with tester insights to explore interactions and unexpected defects.</cell></row>
          <row><cell><strong>Collaborative regression testing</strong></cell><cell>Bug bashes or whole-team walkthroughs of critical flows. Builds awareness of product state and risk areas; useful when automation is immature or as a learning exercise.</cell></row>
        </table>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Traceability</heading>
          <paragraph>Traceability between user stories, requirements, acceptance criteria, and test cases is key. Lightweight traceability (e.g., tagging tests to user stories) helps maintain confidence in frequent releases without slowing delivery.</paragraph>
        </key-box>
      </section>

      <section id="s1-glossary">
        <h2>Chapter 1 Glossary</h2>
        <glossary>
          <term>Acceptance Test-Driven Development (ATDD)</term>
          <definition>A collaborative approach where acceptance criteria are defined as tests before implementation, helping ensure delivered functionality meets stakeholder expectations.</definition>

          <term>Bug Bash</term>
          <definition>A time-boxed, collaborative test activity where the whole team explores the product to find defects and increase awareness of risk areas.</definition>

          <term>Edge Case</term>
          <definition>A scenario that occurs at an extreme operating parameter; often uncovered by exploratory or holistic testing rather than predefined scripts.</definition>

          <term>End-to-End Testing (E2E)</term>
          <definition>Testing that verifies integration across the entire application and, if relevant, multiple systems or services, typically focused on critical user flows.</definition>

          <term>Feature Toggle</term>
          <definition>A technique allowing features to be turned on or off in production without redeployment; supports selective exposure and canary releases.</definition>

          <term>Formal Testing</term>
          <definition>Testing that emphasizes precision and formalization, deriving test cases from explicitly defined requirements; useful for compliance and risk control.</definition>

          <term>Hardening Iteration</term>
          <definition>An iteration focused on stabilization and system-wide testing before release. May indicate insufficient attention to quality during regular iterations.</definition>

          <term>Holistic Testing</term>
          <definition>An approach that extends beyond planned test activities to encompass a system-wide view of quality, incorporating continuous testing and multiple perspectives (customer, team, organizational).</definition>

          <term>Iteration</term>
          <definition>A fixed timebox in Agile development during which a usable and potentially releasable product increment is created.</definition>

          <term>Regression Testing</term>
          <definition>Testing of a previously tested program following modification to ensure that defects have not been introduced or uncovered in unchanged areas.</definition>

          <term>Test-Driven Development (TDD)</term>
          <definition>A development practice where tests are written before code, supporting early defect detection and a stable codebase.</definition>

          <term>Test Type</term>
          <definition>A group of test activities aimed at testing specific characteristics of a component or system (e.g., functional, non-functional, white-box, black-box).</definition>

          <term>User Journey</term>
          <definition>The path a user takes through an application or across systems to achieve a goal; often the focus of end-to-end testing.</definition>
        </glossary>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="ch2">
      <meta>
        <badge>Chapter 2</badge>
        <badge>60 minutes</badge>
        <badge>K2 Focus: Understand</badge>
      </meta>
      <title>People and Teams</title>

      <key-box>
        <heading>Learning Objectives</heading>
        <list type="check">
          <item>Compare generalization and specialization within a team</item>
          <item>Give examples of how to motivate business representatives to perform test activities</item>
          <item>Summarize how the whole team approach can assist the development team</item>
          <item>Explain how and when to use tissue testers</item>
        </list>
      </key-box>

      <section id="ch2-intro">
        <h3>Introduction</h3>
        <paragraph>In Agile software development projects, people and tools form the foundation for delivering quality at speed. The whole team approach emphasizes that quality is a shared responsibility among developers, testers, and business representatives who collaborate closely. Teams are typically composed of multi-disciplinary or cross-functional members. While specialists bring deep expertise, generalists adapt across roles, enabling greater flexibility and shared workload. Activating and motivating business representatives to contribute to testing through early involvement in defining acceptance criteria, reviewing test results, and participating in exploratory testing enhances product quality and alignment with business goals. This collaboration also benefits developers because sharing testing insights reduces defects and accelerates feedback. Agile teams may also engage tissue testers — external testers who provide a "fresh eyes" perspective to uncover defects early.</paragraph>
      </section>

      <section id="s2-1">
        <h2>2.1 Whole Team Approach</h2>
        <paragraph>The essence of the whole team approach lies in testers, developers, and business representatives working together as an Agile team in every step of the development process. Generalization and specialization of roles directly impact how test activities are distributed, owned, and improved. Agile promotes a whole team approach to quality, where everyone owns quality regardless of title or position.</paragraph>

        <h3>2.1.1 Generalization and Specialization within a Team</h3>
        <paragraph>Agile testers are typically <strong>generalizing T-shaped specialists</strong>. They maintain deep expertise in testing and broad knowledge across multiple disciplines like coding, business analysis, and DevOps. This supports cross-functional collaboration and enables flexibility in team composition.</paragraph>

        <compare>
          <card type="pos">
            <heading>Generalization</heading>
            <list type="ul">
              <item>Multiple team members can perform a certain activity</item>
              <item>Supports a sustainable pace and reduces bottlenecks</item>
              <item>Enhances team resilience</item>
              <item>Encourages shared ownership of quality</item>
              <item>Essential in continuous delivery environments</item>
            </list>
          </card>
          <card type="pos">
            <heading>Specialization</heading>
            <list type="ul">
              <item>Deep expertise in specific test tasks</item>
              <item>Required for test techniques, exploratory testing, test automation, usability testing</item>
              <item>Testers preserve specialization while developing broader skills</item>
              <item>Context-driven balance (complex/regulated domains may need more specialists; lean startups may prefer generalists)</item>
            </list>
          </card>
        </compare>

        <paragraph>Agile teams strive to <strong>minimize silos</strong> by encouraging knowledge sharing and pairing. <strong>Mob programming and mob testing</strong> blur roles by bringing the whole team (business reps, developers, testers) together to work on a single task simultaneously.</paragraph>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Testers' Role in Generalization</heading>
          <paragraph>Testers often take the lead in helping others apply quality-focused practices such as <strong>BDD</strong>, <strong>exploratory testing</strong>, and <strong>test automation</strong>. They learn from developers about implementation details to better assess risks and design tests, preserving their specialization while contributing to generalization.</paragraph>
        </key-box>

        <paragraph>In multi-team Agile environments (e.g., SAFe, LeSS), the whole team approach extends beyond individual teams. Cross-team coordination on quality standards, integration testing, and defect ownership at team boundaries becomes essential. Testers often participate in <strong>communities of practice</strong> to share knowledge across teams.</paragraph>
      </section>

      <section id="s2-1-2">
        <h3>2.1.2 Motivating Business Representatives to Participate in Testing</h3>
        <paragraph>Quality is a shared responsibility across the whole team. Business representatives define product quality and should participate in test activities. Motivating them begins by involving them early in the test process, especially in defining acceptance criteria and formulating business-facing tests.</paragraph>

        <h4>Key Practices to Motivate Business Representatives</h4>
        <list type="check">
          <item><strong>ATDD, BDD, and Specification by Example</strong> — anchor the business representative's role in clarifying behavior through concrete, testable examples</item>
          <item><strong>Embedding testability into user stories</strong> during backlog refinement ensures acceptance criteria are concrete and tied to verifiable test results</item>
          <item><strong>Visibility via dashboards</strong> — coverage, defect trends, and quality-risk metrics help business representatives understand product quality and where testing adds value</item>
          <item><strong>Business metrics</strong> — customer satisfaction, support costs, feature adoption link testing to product validation</item>
          <item><strong>Shared ownership in daily collaboration</strong> — actively shaping "done" during iteration planning and refinement; presence during bug bashes or usability testing</item>
          <item><strong>Recognition during retrospectives and demos</strong> — reinforces their role in quality and keeps them engaged</item>
        </list>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Key Takeaway</heading>
          <paragraph>With clear expectations, access to relevant information, and continuous opportunities to influence outcomes, business representatives are more likely to see testing as a core part of their responsibilities and a powerful lever for delivering successful products.</paragraph>
        </key-box>
      </section>

      <section id="s2-1-3">
        <h3>2.1.3 Supporting the Developers</h3>
        <paragraph>The whole team approach assists developers by embedding quality-focused collaboration throughout the software development lifecycle. Continuous interaction between developers, testers, and business representatives builds a shared understanding of quality goals and potential risks, leading to better technical and business decisions.</paragraph>

        <h4>How Testers Support Developers</h4>
        <list type="ul">
          <item><strong>Early test feedback</strong> reduces defect costs and supports rapid corrective action (ATDD, BDD)</item>
          <item><strong>Clarifying acceptance criteria</strong> through examples improves specification by example and alignment between code and business expectations</item>
          <item><strong>Coaching developers</strong> to write better component and component-integration tests for higher code coverage</item>
          <item><strong>Enabling safe refactoring</strong> — continuous testing gives developers confidence to evolve the codebase</item>
          <item><strong>Automating tests early</strong> enables faster detection of integration defects and facilitates CI/CD pipelines</item>
          <item><strong>Contributing to code reviews</strong> from a quality and risk perspective</item>
          <item><strong>Participating in exploratory test sessions</strong> together — mutual learning elevates overall competence</item>
          <item><strong>Insights into real user behavior</strong> through usability sessions and production analytics help build user-aligned software</item>
          <item><strong>Early involvement of operations, security, and testers</strong> helps design solutions that are easier to deploy, observe, and secure in production</item>
        </list>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Result</heading>
          <paragraph>By embedding these perspectives from the start, developers can make architectural choices that balance functionality with quality characteristics, ultimately speeding up delivery while increasing confidence in the system's readiness for real-world use.</paragraph>
        </key-box>
      </section>

      <section id="s2-2">
        <h2>2.2 Tissue Testers</h2>
        <paragraph><strong>Tissue testers</strong> (also known as fresh-eyes testers) are temporary testers, external to the team, who provide fast, informal feedback on a product or feature in development. They are most effective when used in early phases of design or feature implementation, before teams commit to expensive development or infrastructure decisions. The idea is to briefly expose a new idea, interface, or interaction to someone unfamiliar with it to detect usability defects, confusing behavior, or misleading flows.</paragraph>

        <h4>Characteristics</h4>
        <list type="ul">
          <item>Typically people from outside the team or project (e.g., a colleague from another team)</item>
          <item>Short-term involvement — after they have seen the product once, they are no longer unbiased</item>
          <item>Their special value as "fresh eyes" diminishes after first exposure</item>
          <item>Lightweight, transient nature — like a tissue, use once and discard for that purpose</item>
        </list>

        <h4>When to Use</h4>
        <list type="check">
          <item>Early phases of design or feature implementation</item>
          <item>Exploratory testing, usability testing, or assumption-checking where quick feedback is valuable but too early for rigorous validation</item>
          <item>Before refining an interaction or screen flow to identify potential issues</item>
        </list>

        <h4>Important Considerations</h4>
        <list type="ul">
          <item><strong>Do not over-explain</strong> — introducing bias destroys their fresh-eyed view</item>
          <item><strong>Does not replace structured testing</strong> — it should precede or complement it</item>
          <item><strong>Primary value</strong> is revealing early misalignments between design intent and actual user comprehension</item>
          <item>Quick to run and do not require recruiting external users, making them useful in Agile and DevOps contexts</item>
        </list>

        <key-box>
          <heading>Key Takeaway</heading>
          <paragraph>Tissue testers provide a lightweight, transient source of unbiased feedback early in development. Use them once for fresh perspective, then move to structured testing for rigorous validation.</paragraph>
        </key-box>
      </section>

      <section id="s2-glossary">
        <h2>Chapter 2 Glossary</h2>
        <glossary>
          <term>Acceptance Test-Driven Development (ATDD)</term>
          <definition>A collaborative approach where acceptance criteria are defined as tests before implementation, inviting business representatives into meaningful dialogue with the team.</definition>

          <term>Behavior-Driven Development (BDD)</term>
          <definition>A collaborative approach that uses concrete, testable examples to clarify behavior and align business expectations with development.</definition>

          <term>Community of Practice</term>
          <definition>A group of people who share a concern or passion for something they do and learn how to do it better as they interact regularly; used in multi-team Agile to share quality knowledge.</definition>

          <term>Generalizing Specialist (T-Shaped)</term>
          <definition>A team member with deep expertise in one area (the vertical bar of the T) and broad knowledge across multiple disciplines (the horizontal bar), enabling flexibility and cross-functional collaboration.</definition>

          <term>Mob Programming / Mob Testing</term>
          <definition>An approach where the whole team works together simultaneously on a single task, blurring traditional role boundaries.</definition>

          <term>Tissue Tester (Fresh-Eyes Tester)</term>
          <definition>A temporary, external tester who provides fast, informal feedback early in development. Their unbiased perspective is valuable only for a single exposure.</definition>

          <term>Whole Team Approach</term>
          <definition>An Agile principle where everyone — developers, testers, and business representatives — shares responsibility for quality throughout the development process.</definition>
        </glossary>
      </section>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>

  <toc>
    <item id="ch1" status="active">Chapter 1: Test Strategy and Test Approach Challenges</item>
    <item id="ch2" status="active">Chapter 2: People and Teams</item>
    <item id="ch3" status="pending">Chapter 3: Test Management and Test Process Improvement (pending)</item>
    <item id="ch4" status="pending">Chapter 4: Shift Left (pending)</item>
    <item id="ch5" status="pending">Chapter 5: Agile Approaches and Test Techniques (pending)</item>
    <item id="ch6" status="pending">Chapter 6: Test Automation and Test Tools (pending)</item>
  </toc>

  <footer-text>Generated from ISTQB® CTAL-AT Syllabus v2.0 — Chapters 1–2 Review</footer-text>
</syllabus>
